现如今 当然了 在全美
But now, of course, all over the United States of America
乃至全世界 互联网正在彻头彻尾地改变着我们的生活
and all over the world the internet is revolutionizing our lives.
那是 1998 年
It's 1998.
Google 刚刚雇佣了它的第一名员工
Google just hired its first employee,
副总统 Al Gore 在接受媒体采访
and Vice President Al Gore is talking to the press.
这项技术还处于起步阶段
This technology is still in its infancy.
当我和比尔·克林顿总统入主白宫时 只有 50 个网站
When president Bill Clinton and I came into the White House there were only 50 sites.
现在看看
And look at it now.
我在生日那天收到了一束虚拟鲜花
I got a bouquet of virtual flowers on my birthday.
好的 我已经感觉到你的眉毛抬起了
Okay. I can sense your eyebrow arching already.
为什么我要向你展现 20 年前的互联网史？
Why am I playing you some bit of 20-year-old Internet history?
这是因为 我想提醒你 互联网的基础从未改变
It's because I want to remind you that the basics of the Internet are still the same.
当然 现在有不止 50 个站点了 我知道
Sure, there are more than 50 sites now. I get it.
但是 我们仍然在互送虚拟鲜花
But, we're still sending virtual flowers.
从开发人员的角度来看
And from a developer's perspective,
即便互联网已经发生了翻天覆地的变化
if you strip away all our incredible advances,
你仍能看到一切伊始时的客户端 - 服务器模型
you've still got that same client-server model that started it all.
这一模型使分布式网络成为可能
A client-server model that allows for a distributed network.
如今 “无服务器”是开发者口中的一大热门话题
Today, developers talk a lot about going serverless,
听起来就像 Al Gore  提到的客户端 - 服务器模型被废弃了
which sounds like Al Gore's client-server internet just got trashed.
而且 如果我们不小心
And if we're not careful,
基础设施就会被过分地抽象化
we can abstract away so much infrastructure
我们就会忘记 服务器仍然存在 仍然一如既往地运作
that we forget there are still servers out there doing their server thing.
“无服务器”真的意味着“没有服务器”吗？真的吗？
But does serverless literally mean no servers? Really?
或者 只是开发者和服务器之间的关系发生了变化？
Or is the developer's relationship with servers just evolving?
在这一集中 我们将与来自世界各地的人们交谈
In this episode, we are talking with people from around the world
以探索所谓“无服务器”的概念
to explore this thing called serverless.
我是 Saron Yitbarek
I'm Saron Yitbarek,
这里是《代码英雄》 一档来自红帽的原创播客节目
and this is Command Line Heroes. An original podcast from Red Hat.
你知道无线网络在某些地方还有线缆吗？
Did you know wireless internet has wires somewhere?
这是 Andrea Passwater 她就职的公司名叫…
Andrea Passwater works for a company called ...
…“无服务器”
Serverless.
他们创建了一款流行的开源框架 用来开发无服务器应用程序
They created a popular, open source framework for developing serverless applications.
Andrea 注意到 各个组织都渴求着基础设施的进一步抽象化
Andrea is noticing how organizations are hungry for ways to abstract away infrastructure,
而这正是“无服务器”一词总显得前景无限 令人入迷的原因
which is what that magical word serverless is always promising.
我认为这一术语主要是为了传达这样一个事实
I think the term is mostly just supposed to convey the fact that
即如果你是开发者 你开发无服务器应用
as a developer who works in serverless applications
你就不必考虑那些服务器 因为它们都被抽象掉了
that's abstracted for you.
You don't have to worry about those servers.
你只需要写代码并将代码部署到云提供商即可
You just get to code and deploy that code up to a cloud provider
不必担心管理
and not have to worry about the administration.
这就是无服务器的真正含义
That's really what serverless means.
对于 Andrea 来说 无服务器的优势很明显
For Andrea, the attractions of serverless are pretty obvious.
倘若你以无服务器的方式开发应用程序
If you develop applications in a serverless way,
你就可以不必考虑部署和维护的日常工作
it gives you the ability to
not have to think about the mundane parts
你就可以不必考虑部署和维护的日常工作
of deploying that application and maintaining that application.
这意味着 你可以专注于它的商业价值
It just means that you can focus on business value.
你可以专心发挥创造力
You can focus on being creative.
而无服务器的另一大好处是 不太容易重复造轮子
And another big serverless bonus is you're less likely to find yourself reinventing the wheel.
当有像 Auth0 这样可以直接使用的服务存在时
Why would you create your own way to handle authentication
为什么要自己实现一套身份验证方法呢？
when services like Auth0 exist that you can just use and tap into
归根结底
At the end of the day,
无服务器就是为开发人员提供机会
serverless is about giving developers the opportunity to be able to
让他们能更快地按照想法编写程序
more easily and more rapidly build all of these ideas in their heads
实现想要的效果
that they want to get out into the world.
想象一下 你拿了满手的东西
Imagine you've got your arms full of groceries,
正跌跌撞撞地走向一扇门
and you're stumbling toward a door.
这扇门滑开了 以简单、友好…
The door slides open in a simple, friendly-
（“麻烦开一下”）
Allow me.
…的方式 这就是无服务器
... kind of way. That's serverless.
它为你打开了大门 使得开发工作不再那么繁琐
It's opening the door for you, making development a lot less cumbersome.
随着各个组织对混合云环境的逐渐青睐
In fact, as organizations flock toward hybrid cloud setups
以及无服务器运动的发展
and the serverless movement gets underway,
开发的障碍正在消失
the barriers toward development are vanishing.
Andrea 听说过很多“非开发人员参与开发”的故事
Andrea has been hearing a lot of talk about non-developer development.
也就是 一般来说认为自己写不了代码
Sort of stories from people who traditionally thought they couldn't code,
现在却由于无服务器 得以投身软件工程的人的故事
and who are now actually able to get into the software engineering game because of serverless.
他们还能编写工具 自动化自己的工作流程
And able to make these tools that automate their own workflows and stuff like that.
这跟你从事的是什么职业无关
It doesn't matter what job you do.
工作中总会有些事繁琐又枯燥
There's something you do on your job that is so rote,
每天都要做这样的事 你就会想
like you do it every single day and it's this thing that you're like,
“这玩意儿难道不能让电脑替我来吗？”
"You know, couldn't a computer do this for me?"
我开始有这种感觉的时候
I started to feel that way.
我碰巧在一家名为“无服务器”的公司工作
I happened to work at this company called Serverless
他们这样说：“你知道我们的产品能帮到你吧？”
and they were like, "You realize that the product we make can help you with that. Right?"
Andrea 认为 不久之后
Andrea figures that pretty soon
许多从未将自己视为开发人员的人将意识到
a lot of people who never considered themselves developers are going to realize
他们能自己制作简单的应用程序 费用几乎可以忽略不计
they can build simple apps themselves. At essentially no cost.
使用 Lambda 时 我从来不需要为自己制作的任何小型应用付费
With Lambda, I've never had to pay for any of these small applications that I've made.
我可以让机器人为我做一部分工作
I can make these bots that do part of my job for me,
提高工作效率
and I can become more efficient at my job, yes.
我也不必再亲手操办无聊的部分了
But, I also don't have to do that boring stuff anymore.
我可以做些更有趣的事情
I can do something that's more fun.
即使是对于专业开发人员来说
Even for pro developers,
这种“自动门”效果在满手杂物的世界里也是很诱人的
that automatic door effect is pretty tempting in an arms-full-of-groceries kind of world.
我认为 大家都很想要这种效果
I think people are very attracted to the idea that
一两个人的团队 在很短的时间内就完成产品原型
they can get prototypes working with a one- or two-person team
in a very short amount of time.
像是 在几天时间内搞定
Like, a handful of days.
在几天时间内 他们就可以启动原型
They can get a prototype up and running.
这实在是幸事一件 人们渐渐发现
I think it makes it very exciting for people to start realizing
如此这般 他们就能专注于应用功能 使其创造更多价值
that they get to just focus on what drives business value in their application,
就能多考虑他们的产品 多考虑他们的公司
or for their product, for their company.
他们可以专注于商业价值
They get to focus on that business value.
我要再抛出一个术语给你 准备好了吗？
I'm going to throw another term at you. Ready?
“函数即服务”（FaaS）
Functions-as-a-service.
无服务器平台提供的就是这项业务
That's the offering at serverless places
这些平台包括 AWS Lambda 和 Apache OpenWhisk
like AWS Lambda, or Apache OpenWhisk.
“函数即服务”意味着
Functions-as-a-service means
能在有必要时 专门执行单独的函数
a single function can be executed on demand,
只在触发时执行
only when triggered.
这样效率更高
And that's a lot more efficient.
与此同时 对计算能力和运行时间的忧虑也会大大减少
Plus, I'm way less worried about compute capacity and run time.
说到底 无服务器的这一套配置可以相当诱人
End of the day, that serverless deal can be a pretty sweet setup.
有些人甚至开始考虑
In fact, some folks have even started wondering,
我们要把所有业务都迁移到无服务器平台吗？它可以替代容器吗？
are we going all in on serverless? Does it maybe replace containers?
我理解这这种想法
I see the point.
Michael Hausenblas 是 Red Hat OpenShift 团队的开发倡导者
Michael Hausenblas is the developer advocate for the OpenShift® team over at Red Hat.
如果你看一下现在的这些云计算平台
If you look at all of these things we have here,
包括 OpenShift 和 Cloud Foundry 之类
OpenShift and Cloud Foundry and what not,
它们做的很多事 实质上都是抽象化
you have essentially these abstractions.
这样的指导思想从 Heroku 就开始了
This idea that the Heroku, essentially, bent it more or less.
Heroku 是最早的云计算平台之一
对吧？这样能为开发者带来极大方便 无需担心程序会如何运行
Right? This very simple way of, don't worry about how the execution will run,
无需担心整体的图景
don't worry about what it looks like.
只需要给我们代码 我们来处理剩下的工作
Just give us the code and we take care of the rest.
是的 听起来相当不错
Yeah. That sounds pretty good.
这听起来有点儿像是梦想中的“无运维”环境
It kind of sounds like that dream of a “no-ops”environment.
一切都自动化并且抽象化了
Where everything is automated and abstracted away.
就像是开发者版本的极简主义室内设计
It's like the developer's version of minimalist interior design.
在表面上 一切都干净又友好
Nice, clean surfaces.
但是 Michael 想要让你了解你一些现实情况
But, Michael wants to give you a little reality check.
没有运维！对吧？！你懂的 运维会跟变魔术一样消失掉
No ops! Right? You know, it magically just will somehow go away.
HackerNews 和 Twitter 之类的地方到处都是无服务器笑话
You see these jokes on HackerNews and Twitter, and wherever.
无服务器？当然有服务器！
Serverless, of course there are servers!
我知道 当然有 而且也肯定有运维
I know, of course there are. There's operations.
总得有人去做这些 总得有人去架设服务器
Someone has to do that, someone has to rack the servers.
总得有人给操作系统打补丁
Someone has to patch the operating systems.
去创建容器镜像
Someone has to create container images,
因为 你猜猜这些函数会在哪里执行？
because guess where these functions are executing?
当然是在某种计算机上
Of course, in some kind of computer.
这不是零和博弈
It's not a zero-sum game.
“函数即服务”无法直接取代容器
Functions-as-a-service don't outright replace containers.
而只是在工具箱中增加了一个工具
Instead, they add a tool to the tool box.
我还有别的要说
And I've got some more news for you.
使用这种新工具
Using that new tool,
使用无服务器不代表你就能把运维工作全部推给别人
going serverless doesn't just mean the ops is somebody else's problem.
你仍然需要自己考虑自己的运维
You've still got ops of your own to think about.
基础设施侧当然要为运维工作负责
You see there is operations bits on the infrastructure side.
但开发者也并非全无这方面的责任
But, also with the developers.
如果你处于极端情况之下
If you're in an extreme case,
比如说使用 Lambda
using let's say Lambda,
那你根本联系不了管理员 对吧？
then you have zero access to any kind of administrators. Right?
你不能直接给基础设施管理员打电话 或者发短信
You cannot simply call or page an infrastructure administrator.
显然 你的组织之中就得有人接手这部分运维
Obviously, someone in your organization has to do it.
但是 我担心许多组织只看到了无服务器的便捷和便宜
But, I fear that many organizations only see it's so simple and cheap.
这里也不用操心 那里也不用插手
We don't need to move this, and this, and this.
然后忘记了谁需要待命 谁需要负责运维
Then forget about who is on call, and who really is on call?
你对此有策略吗？
Do you have a strategy for that?
如果没有的话 那你得在一头扎进去之前 先制定一个策略
If no, then you might want to come up with a strategy first before you go all in there.
需要有人处于待命状态
Someone needs to be on call.
即使选择了“无服务器”
Even if you do go "serverless,"
你脑子里还是得装着业务的全貌
you still need to have your head wrapped around that bigger picture.
你仍然需要让运维有序进行
You still need to get your operations in order.
我之前抛出那个“函数即服务”术语时
When I threw out that term earlier, functions-as-a-service,
你是不是有过些许畏缩？
did you cringe a little?
过去 基于云的开发为我们带来了大量的 “xx 即服务”的术语
Over the last while cloud-based development has brought us an army of “as-a-service”terms.
我们有基础架构即服务（IaaS）
We've got infrastructure-as-a-service,
平台即服务（PaaS）
we've got platform-as-a-service,
软件即服务（SaaS）、数据即服务（DaaS）
we've got software-as-a-service, data-as-a-service.
数据库即服务（DBaaS）
Database-as-a-service.
你懂我的意思
You get the idea.
如果你难以理解它们的不同 那你并不孤单
If you're having trouble keeping the differences straight,
you're not alone.
这就是我们找来了 Himanshu Pant 的原因
That's why we tracked down Himanshu Pant.
他是位于印度德里的苏格兰皇家银行的技术主管
He's a tech lead at the Royal Bank of Scotland, over in Delhi, India.
他花了多年时间来分析其中的差异
He spent years parsing out the differences here.
这些其他的计算范型
These other computing paradigms
在名称上和无服务器听起来是如此的相似
are so similar sounding in name to serverless
注：本篇中“无服务器”和“函数即服务”两个词等价，且会被互换着使用
以至于 一个人要么容易忘了为什么这些不叫“无服务器”
that one tends to forget,
要么从来没搞懂过这些词跟“无服务器”的区别
or tends to get confused as to why,
this is not being called serverless.
要么干脆不知道为什么无服务器叫做“无服务器”
Or why this is being called a serverless.
无服务器与容器不同
So, serverless is not the same as containers.
无服务器也不是平台即服务
Serverless is not platform-as-a-service.
Himanshu  想将它们之间的界限划清
But Himanshu wanted to nail it down.
“函数即服务”能提供什么 又不能提供什么？
What can functions-as-a-service provide, exactly? And what can't it?
他与我们分享了两则轶事
He shared two anecdotes with us,
一次 他决定使用无服务器 另一次他决定放弃
two times when he figured out when to go with serverless and when to forgo.
第一则轶事来自一次 24 小时黑客马拉松
The first moment came during a 24-hour hackathon.
Himanshu 当时正试图开发一个聊天机器人
Himanshu was trying to make a chat bot.
有各种各样的指标会决定它成功与否
There were various vectors on which this was going to be a sales.
例如逻辑覆盖率
For example, that coverage of logic,
可能的成本 以及可伸缩性
the cost which would be incurred and the scalability.
而我选择在无服务器环境下完成这项工作
I sat down to do this work in serverless.
我开发它的时候 我意识到成本这个要素
As I did, I realized that cost aspect was one aspect,
而成本控制这方面是我的长项
which kind of really tippedthe skill in my favor.
因此 即使其他所有的参与者
So even though all the other participants,
都有更好的…覆盖率
they had a much better ... I would say coverage,
或者说是逻辑覆盖率
or maybe coverage of logic,
或者说在自然语言处理（NLP）方面做得更好
or the NLP situations or their scenarios.
但是 就成本和可伸缩性而言
But, as far as cost is concerned, and scalability,
我是手操胜券的
I was going hands down to win over there
因为有了无服务器 成本就完全取决于
because with serverless it all depended on
人们在该聊天机器人上所进行调用的次数
how many invocations people are doing on that chat bot.
只有调用之后 函数才会执行
Accordingly, the functions will be triggered.
这是一个我十分乐意采用无服务器的用例
This was one use case when I was very much happy to do serverless,
因为成本 - 没有成本
because of the cost - there was no cost.
以及更快的开发时间
Faster development time, and to be honest,
而且老实说 当时还并不完全是生产规模级别的工作负载
it was not exactly a production-scale workload at that moment.
我可以使用平台上的某些新兴工具
I could make do with the somewhat infant tooling of the platform.
这对我而言是一次胜利
It was a win for me.
真不错 那时候使用无服务器是合理的
Nice. That was a time when serverless made sense.
但是 在 Himanshu 目前供职的银行里
But at the bank Himanshu is working in right now,
人们正在将他们的系统从旧版迁移到云端
they're migrating their systems from legacy to cloud.
而这提出了不同的目标
And that's bringing up different kinds of goals.
我们在试着找出适合每一项业务的计算范型
We are trying to see which workload can go on to which paradigm.
比如 IaaS、BaaS、FaaS
I should just go into IS, BAS, FAS,
分别意为：“基础设施即服务”，“银行即服务”，和“函数即服务”。
这显然是属于企业领域的
obviously the ones who come down to enterprise space.
有几个原因让我们放弃使用无服务器 其一是供应商依赖
You need to see that there are no aspects, like number one, let’s say vendor lock-in.
以及第二 这项技术尚未得到广泛的验证
And number two, that technology should be proven, extensively.
对于像银行业这样规避风险的行业而言 这点尤为重要
More so for a risk-averse industry like, you know, the banking sector.
Risk-averse: 通常译为“风险厌恶”
即：在相同的期望回报率下，偏好风险更小的方案
这时我们决定采用平台即服务（PaaS）
This is where a platform-as-a-service,
因为它经过更多验证
but still has a better proving,
整体性能更好
and a better capability,
可用的工具也更多
and a better tooling kind of takes the upper hand.
Himanshu 正在研究自己的需求以及他自己的舒适区
Himanshu is looking at his own needs, and his own comfort levels,
并研究哪些云计算范型应用在哪些业务上是合理的
and curating which workloads make sense in which cloud computing paradigm.
假设 某位听众在一家贸易商店工作
Let's say a listener is working on a trading shop,
他想构建某种东西 入门级别的
and he wants to build something, just an entry one.
对于他或者她来说 无服务器可能并不是真正合适的选择
For him or her, serverless may not really be apt
因为在那种在特定机器的应用程序中 延迟可能是不该出现的
because the latency may not really be desirable in that kind of a machine-particular application.
归根结底 做决定之前得多考量
End of the day, it's a measured approach.
而不是将所有东西都丢进一个桶里
Instead of throwing everything into one bucket.
当你思考 哪一种基于云的架构适用于手头的任务时
When we're thinking about which cloud-based architecture is actually right
for the work we want to do,
还有一件事需要考虑
there's one more thing to consider.
所有的抽象化 所有解放你双手的东西
How all that abstracting, all that taking things off your hands,
最终如何改变的不仅仅是我们的工作方式 还改变了产品本身
can end up changing not just our work lives, but the finished work itself.
抽象掉一部分工作量 可供自定义的空间也会减少
Abstracting away part of our workload can mean less ability to customize.
想象你买了一辆车
Think of a car you bought off the lot.
它管用 它能开
It works. It drives.
但是接着想象一下 你自己组装的车
But then, think of a car you built on your own.
你想怎么开它 就能怎么开它
That one works the way you decided it would work.
这是有代价的
It comes at a cost.
Rania Khalaf 是 IBM 研究部门的 AI 工程总监
Rania Khalaf is the director of AI Engineering at IBM research.
在使用无服务器应用程序时
In using these serverless applications,
你可能无法完全控制程序运行的方式
you may not have full control of everything that's going on.
你无法控制全盘计划 或是程序何时何地运行
You don't have control of scheduling, or when they'll run, or where.
这是一种权衡 对吧？
There's a trade off taking place, right?
使用无服务器 可能就代表无法进行精细控制
Fine-grain control may slip when you're using serverless.
它对于终端用户而言 抽象化了如此之多的东西
It abstracts so much away from the end-user
以至于 如果你想要更多控制权
that if you do want to have more control,
想要不同的规划
different scheduling,
更多制衡
more checks and balances,
函数运行的不同时长
different values on how long a function can run for.
等等等等
So on and so forth.
你恐怕就得自己进入系统 动手修改
Then you really want to be able to get in there and tinker,
魔改过后 或许还要自行部署
and maybe create your own deployments.
这种需求会需要无服务器做出前所未有的改变
That would require something new, though.
作为应答 开源社区为自身打造出了全新的无服务器平台
A new kind of serverless that open source communities are already building for themselves.
Rania 和她的 IBM 团队参与了该运动
Rania and her team of IBMers are part of that movement.
我们首先制作了一种编程语言…
We first worked on a language that was ...
它基本上是 JavaScript 的扩展
It’s basically JavaScript extensions
可以创建多线程交互服务的组合
to let you create these multi-threaded interactive service compositions
为你提供一种更加轻量级服务的方式
as a starting point to give you a lighter-weight way.
大约在同一时间
That was around the same time that
云、微服务和平台即服务开始真正兴起
that cloud and microservices and platform-as-a-service were really picking up.
将这两种趋势结合起来
Just combining these two trends and saying,
就有了这种想法 - 将小的组件互相组合 以此来实现复杂的功能
there is this idea of being able to build higher order function from many small pieces
这些组件可以是你自己写的 也可以来自其他人
that may or may not come from you.
Rania 和她的团队负责构建 Apache OpenWhisk
Rania and her team were building Apache OpenWhisk.
一款开源的函数平台
An open source functions platform.
*即“函数即服务”的平台
我们从一开始就开源了 OpenWhisk
With OpenWhisk, from the beginning, we made it open source.
一大原因是 让社区和我们一起参与进来
A big part of that was to really enable the community to participate with us.
但是 同时也是为了揭掉外包装
But also to peel away the covers.
将控制权交给
And give control to the people that
想要运行自己的无服务器计算环境的人们
are wanting to operate their own serverless computing environments,
以便他们能够根据自己的需求对其进行自定义
so that they can customize it to their needs.
在有需要时 将它们置身于自己的控制之中
Maybe put in their own controls,
看看它实际上是如何运行的 以对其进行更好的控制
see how it really works, and control it better.
而且 我们还可以提供更加精细的控制
But, also provide the kind of finer-grain control
如果它仅仅是一项服务 客户就不会有这种控制权
that people wouldn't have with it if it was only offered as a service.
将控制权交还给想要运行自己的无服务器运行环境的人
Giving control back to anyone who wants to operate their own serverless environment.
这是无服务器的下一步
It's next-stage serverless.
OpenWhisk 推出后 其他无服务器平台也有样学样
Joining OpenWhisk, you've got other open source platforms
比如 Fission 和 Gestalt
like Fission and Gestalt.
我们开始看到 无服务器的赛场上 平台们正在变得更具适应性
We start to see the serverless arena evolving into something more adaptable,
而且功能更为强大
and more powerful than before.
为了真正了解为什么开源版的无服务器很重要
To really get why an open source version of serverless matters,
我与 OpenWhisk 的创始人之一进行了谈话
I got chatting with one of the founders of OpenWhisk.
嗨 Rodric 最近好吗？
Hi, Rodric. How is it going?
不错 你好吗？谢谢你邀请我参与节目
Good. How are you? Thanks for having me on.
Rodric Rabbah 是构思并创立 OpenWhisk 的三位开发者之一
Rodric Rabbah was one of the three developers who conceived of,
and founded, OpenWhisk.
以下是我们的谈话
Here is our conversation.
别人听了可能会很困惑 也可能会窃笑
It tends to be confusing for others or tends to get snickers,
因为他们可能会想：
because people tend to think,
“倘若没有服务器 你要怎么做计算呢？”
“How could you possibly compute without servers?”
是的 服务器仍然存在
Right. Server is there somewhere,
只是我不必去费心考虑它
it's just I don't have to worry about it.
完全正确 这就是这个模式的美妙之处
Exactly. That's really the beauty of this model.
只要你试过用无服务器的方式来开发软件
When you start developing in a serverless style,
你就再也不想回到过去了
you never really want to go back.
你知道 如今我已经置身其中 将近 4 年了
You know, I've been in it for close to four years now,
也开发了一些达到生产质量的应用程序
and I've developed some production-quality applications.
这是我如今惟一的开发方式
This is the only way I develop now.
如果你叫我找一台服务器来 安装操作系统
If you tell me I have to provision a machine and install an OS,
这对我而言 完全是陌生的
it's completely foreign to me.
甚至 我还记不记得该怎么做 这都不好说
I'm not even sure I'd know how to do it anymore.
嗯 你知道吗 你这样说的时候 无服务器听起来像是给开发者减负
Yeah. When you put it like that, it sounds like a huge load off,you know?
当最初听说无服务器时
Because when you initially hear of serverless,
至少我会想：
at least I think,
“好家伙 我要学的东西又多了一样 ”
"Man, it's yet another thing I have to learn."
但是 当你这样说的时候 听起来不错
But, when you put it that way it sounds nice.
这确实听起来很棒
It does sound nice.
然而 你也能意识到 我们不能把话说得太满
Then you have to realize that you have to take a little bit of air out of the bubble.
它不是万能药
It's not a silver bullet.
有哪些风险或问题
What are some of the surprising risks or issues
是人们在起步时可能没有看到 或者没有察觉的呢？
that people may not see or be aware of when they get started?
我认为缺乏透明度可能是最大的问题
I think the lack of transparency is possibly the biggest one.
这有点儿让我想起了
It's sort of reminiscent to me of sort of
那些提高了计算机抽象水平的技术
the technology that came about when new languages came about
and raised a level of abstraction relative to the computer.
和它们一样 现在的无服务器技术使人吃惊
It's a similar kind of, sort of, startling effect in serverless today.
也就是：“写一个函数 之后就能立马部署它”
In that you write, typically a function, then you just deploy that function.
它可以立即运行
It's instantaneously available to run,
比如在 web 上作为 APIN 点
say on the web as an APIN point.
它可以大规模伸缩
It scales massively.
我的意思是 你什么都不用做 也可以运行数千个实例
I mean, you can run thousands of instances without any work on your part.
但要是哪里出了问题 那该如何调试呢？
But, if something goes wrong, it's like, how do I debug this?
或者 如果我想检查函数失灵时的上下文环境 这又该怎么办呢？
Or I actually want to inspect the context within which my function failed.
通常 这些功能在进程内运行 与你隔离 -
Typically, these functions run within processes, are isolated from you -
你甚至不能登录计算机 查看你的代码在何处运行
you can't even log into the machine to see where your code is running.
它们可能在封闭的容器环境之中运行
They might run in container environments that are closed off.
你不知道里面有什么
You don't know what's in them.
哪怕一点点透明度都很难获得
It becomes hard for you to get that little bit of transparency.
这时候 工具就能派上用场了
This is where tools will eventually help.
但是 目前工具的缺乏
But, the lack of tools sort of makes that
让透明度的问题变成了一个大家都踩的坑
pretty significant pitfall for people to get their heads around.
说得不错
That was really good.
那么让我们回到 OpenWhisk
Okay. Let's go back to OpenWhisk, alright?
请给我说说关于它的事情
Tell me about that.
该项目在 Amazon Lambda 宣布推出产品的那一刻就开始了
The project started right around the time Amazon Lambda announced their offering,
那正是无服务器真正成为术语
which was really where serverless started to get into the nomenclature
并且开始在技术领域获得关注的时刻
and started to gain mindshare in the space.
当我们看到 Lambda 时 我们开始思索：
When we saw Lambda, we started thinking,
“这里有许多技术需要开发
“There is a lot of technology here that has to be developed.
我们不仅需要为新的云计算方式进行开发
Not just at the base layer in terms of a new cloud computer,
也要为其上的编程模型进行开发
but really in terms of your programming model that you put on top of it
让开发者能更方便地使用无服务器
to make it more easily accessible to programmers.
你知道 由于出自 IBM 研究所 我们拥有相当强大的技术
You know, coming out of IBM research, we had pretty strong ...
比如编程语言设计方面的技术
set of skills around programming language design,
以及关于编译器和运行时的专业技能
compiler expertise, and run time expertise.
我们的团队很小 基本上只有三个人…
A small team of us, basically three people-
哇
Wow.
…聚集在一起 做了最初的开发和原型
... got together to essentially do the initial development and prototyped what became,
最终成品就是 OpenWhisk  带有命令行工具
eventually, OpenWhisk, with respect to the command line tools,
这些工具现在可以说得上是无服务器的编程接口
which is really the programming interface for serverless today.
先提出它的编程模型
The programming model concepts,
然后再决定它该支持怎么样的架构
and then the actual architecture that it has to support,
也就是 “函数即服务”具体该怎么实现
essentially, this function of the service model
才能让开发者获得无服务器的全部好处
and give you all the benefits that serverless espouses.
请注意 真正的起源是 Amazon Lambda 的出现
The genesis was really Amazon Lambda coming on the scene and saying
它面世时 这种新的计算模型也宣告面世
there's this new model of computing. Pay attention.
那么 打造它花了多长时间？或者说 第一个版本什么时候出现的
How long did it take? Or the first version anyway.
实际上很快
It happened quite fast.
事实上 当 IBM 宣布 IBM OpenWhisk... 那时候它还叫这个
In fact, when IBM announced ... Well, it was at the time IBM OpenWhisk.
从我们第一次提交 到那时候 才一年
It was one year to the date from our first commit.
哇 我的天哪
Wow. Oh my goodness.
其实挺厉害的
That was quite exciting.
哇 我的天哪
Wow. Oh my goodness.
其实挺厉害的
That was quite exciting.
这确实很令人印象深刻
That's really impressive.
它其实最开始不叫 OpenWhisk 只有 Whisk 对吗？
Actually, when it first started, it wasn't OpenWhisk, it was just Whisk. Right?
没错 Whisk 是内部名称
Whisk was the internal name, that's right.
I'm responsible for the name.
我取的这个名字
The idea behind the name was to move quickly and nimbly.
这个名字隐含的意思是 迅速而又灵活地行动
不错
Nice.
你“搅拌”了一个函数 就可以了
You whip up a function and there it is.
你可以将其放入烤箱中烘焙
You can put it in the oven and bake it.
真是绝妙 我看到这个词 我肯定想的是鸡蛋
That's wonderful, because I was definitely thinking eggs when I saw that.
我会想着 打蛋 “搅拌”鸡蛋
I was thinking, let's whisk some eggs.
对 这个名字受到过一些好评 也有一些恶评
Right. We've done some positives and some negatives on the name.
当我们开源一项技术
When we open source a technology,
并将其放到 GitHub 上时
and sort of put it out on GitHub,
我们会在加上 Open 前缀 以强调该技术开源开放
we put the open prefix on it to sort of emphasize that this is open as in open source
可以自由使用、自由下载、自由贡献
and free to use, free to download, free to contribute to.
我们将其开源是为了
And our goal in putting it on open source was really
拉高无服务器平台的总体质量
to sort of raise the bar in terms of what's available to execute these days
as a serverless platform.
对我们来说 重要的是要建立一个平台 不仅可以用于生产环境
It was important to us to sort of build a platform that is not only production-ready,
还可以与全世界共享
and share it with the world,
而且还可用于学术研究或一般性研究
but also to make it possible for academic research or research in general.
也许因为出自 IBM 的研究机构 我们有点儿在意这个
Maybe coming out of IBM research, we cared about that a little too much.
但是 这是有所回报的
But, it sort of paid off
我知道有一些大学真的会在研究中使用 OpenWhisk
in that I know of universities that actually use OpenWhisk
包括康奈尔和普林斯顿
for their own research - from Cornell to Princeton.
我去过好几所大学
I've gone to several universities like Brown, Williams College, MIT, CMU,
包括布朗大学、威廉姆斯学院、麻省理工、卡内基·梅隆
并且进行了一些讲座 鼓励学生去
and I've given talks with the purpose of encouraging students
研究关于无服务器和服务器功能的问题
to really look at the problems around serverless and functions of the service.
研究其工具、编程模型
The tooling, the programming model,
并且使他们对技术感兴趣
and get them excited about the technology.
向他们展示这样的一条道路：
Showing them that there's a path
如果他们参与了 OpenWhisk 的开发
to where if they actually contribute to the open source project,
IBM 的云计算平台会很快实装这些修改
it's picked up by IBM cloud functions and run in production,
一般来说 在贡献提交之后的一周内就能实装
usually within a week.
哇 这么快
Wow. That's so fast.
有些人会很吃惊
That's been surprising to some people.
这是个非常高效的过程
That's a super-efficient process.
它证明了我们的开源开发方式的优越性
It's really a testament to how we develop a lot of technology in the open.
我们没有采用保留部分闭源组件的“部分开源”模式
It's not an open core model where there are some components that have been held back.
在 IBM 云上运行的 就是 Apache OpenWhisk 项目本身
What's running in the IBM cloud is really what's in the Apache OpenWhisk project.
当你思索无服务器的未来
When you think about the future of serverless
以及我们所选择的前进道路时
and the options we may have moving forward,
你是否觉得 它们会不可避免地奔向开源
do you feel like they will inevitably be open?
我想 最近对于开源的价值有一场激烈的争议
I think there's a raging debate these days about the value of open source,
尤其是在云计算领域
especially in the cloud.
是的 没错
Right, yeah.
说起人们转向云计算的原因
If you consider why people go to the cloud,
或者他们可能会厌恶云计算的原因
or why they might have aversions to go into the cloud,
我们就逃不开供应商锁定的问题
it's this whole concept of vendor lock-in
丧失透明度
being ... losing transparency.
开源在一定程度上缓解这些问题
Open source has played an important role in sort of alleviating some of these issues.
然后再看看类似 Kubernetes 的服务
Then you look at efforts like Kubernetes,
作为容器管理系统 它横扫了整个云计算领域
which is just gobbling up the cloud in terms of a container and management system.
它多成功啊
How successful that's been.
如果你正在做的事情涉及到容器
If you're doing something that even touches containers,
鉴于它的主导地位 “保持闭源” 真的还是个可选项吗
does it even warrant having a discussion about keeping it closed source,
giving how dominate it is?
我倾向于认为 开放是有好处的
I tend to think that openness helps.
从开发人员的角度来看 这很有吸引力
It's compelling from developers’ perspectives.
对于未来的无服务器生态 及其工具、项目以及服务
When you think about the future of the serverless ecosystem and tools,
and projects, and services that we're going to see,
你怎么想？
what does that look like?
对你来说 无服务器的未来是什么样的？
What does the future of serverless look like for you?
我认为 它会让你越来越少思考底层技术
I think you start to think less and less about the underlying technology,
越来越多地考虑编程体验以及围绕它的工具：
and it becomes more and more about the programming experience,
and the tooling around it.
用于调试的工具
The tooling for debugging,
用于部署管理的工具
the tooling for deployment management,
用于性能分析的工具
the tooling for performance analysis,
用于安全的工具
the tooling for security.
我认为 这些全都非常重要
All of these are sort of fundamentally important, I think.
函数运行的底层机制
The underlying mechanics of how you run your function,
无论它们是在容器中运行 还是在一些未来的技术下运行
whether they run in a container or some future technology,
也无论它们是在一个云上运行 还是在多个云上运行
whether you can run them on one cloud, or multi-cloud,
我认为 这些都会被抽象化
I think fades into the background.
有点儿像是 Kubernetes 在容器以及容器管理方面所做的事情
Kind of like what Kubernetes did for containers and container management.
在最上方抽象出一层
In a similar way there's a layer that's going to come on top,
这一层是“函数即服务”的函数层面 即“无服务器”的特性所在
which is the function of the service layering to give you that kind of serverless notion.
在此之下是新的中间件 它起到非常重要的作用
Then it's really about what's the new middleware that you're putting on top of it.
赋能授权给开发者 就是让他们能利用新的云计算技术的优势
How are you empowering developers to really take advantage of this new cloud computer
与此同时 使他们体验良好 免于琐事折磨
and the toiling that you're going to put around it to make their experience pleasant.
你说的授权赋能 会带来怎样的影响？
Yeah. What does that empowerment look like?
一言以蔽之 就是提高效率
Efficiency, to put it in one word.
“赋能”就是让开发者能专心做对他们来说有价值的事
It's the ability to just focus on the things that are of value to me as a developer,
或者对公司有价值的事 如果他们为公司工作的话
or the value to my company if I'm working at a corporation.
这样能更快地创新
It's more rapid innovation that, then, you beget out of that,
因为你的脑细胞得到了解放
because you freed up your brain cells
你不用去考虑基础设施怎样和如何伸缩
to not think about infrastructure and how things scale,
也不必去考虑在硬件层面如何保障安全
and how things are secured at the hardware level.
现在 你可以全心全意地创新
Now you can really innovate
将脑力投入到更快的创新中去
in terms of rededicating that brain power to just innovating more rapidly,
从而为你的终端用户带来更多的价值
delivering more value to your end-users.
我想把这一切都归结于更高的效率
I'd lump that all into just better efficiency.
Rodric Rabbah 是 OpenWhisk 的一位创始人
Rodric Rabbah is a founder of OpenWhisk.
还记得我在这一期节目开始的时候所说的吗？
Remember what I said at the top of the show?
互联网所基于的那种 传统的客户端 - 服务器模型并不会消失
That old client-server model that the internet is based on really isn't going anywhere.
改变的是 - 我是说 彻底改变的是
What's changing, and I mean radically changing,
我们对服务器的视角
is the way we think about those servers.
所谓无服务器世界的理想
In a so-called serverless world,
希望我们专注于代码本身
the hope is that we concentrate on the code itself
而不用担心基础架构
and don't have to worry about infrastructure.
但是 我们所选择的抽象等级
But the level of abstraction we select,
以及如何保持对于未被抽象的工作的控制
and how we maintain control over work we don't abstract away,
才是无服务器世界真正有趣的地方
are where that serverless world gets interesting.
无服务器 最终 应当为开发人员赋能授权
Serverless should, ultimately, be about developer empowerment.
使他们免于打补丁、进行伸缩和管理基础设施
The freedom from patching, scaling, and infrastructure management.
但是 与此同时
But, at the same time,
我们应当保持对整体图景的好奇心
we have to stay curious about how that big picture works
即使某些任务遭到了抽象 也不该视而不见
even as we abstract some tasks away.
自问 我要放弃哪些控制权
We're going to be asking, what controls am I giving up
而我要收回的 又是哪些控制权？
and what controls do I want to take back?
下一集是我们史诗般的第二季的大结局
Next episode it's our epic season two finale.
《代码英雄》将会…
Command Line Heroes is taking...
…踏上征途 前往火星
...a journey to Mars.
我们将会了解 NASA 的火星探测器如何开始一场开源革命
We're learning how NASA's martian rover is kicking off an open source revolution of its own.
并且我们将与 NASA 喷气推进实验室的 CTO 进行交流
And we're hanging out with the CTO at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
不用谢
No biggie.
了解开源如何塑造太空探索的未来
To learn how open source is shaping the future of space exploration.
与此同时 如果你想要更加深入地研究无服务器开发的问题
Meantime, if you want to dive deeper into the question of serverless development,
或是在这一季里我们所探索过的任何主题
or any of the subjects we've explored this season,
请访问 redhat.com/commandlineheroes 查看免费资源
check out the free resources waiting for you at redhat.com/commandlineheroes.
在那里
While you're there,
你甚至可以为我们自己的代码英雄游戏作出贡献
you can even contribute to our very own Command Line Heroes game.
我是 Saron Yitbarek 感谢收听 编程不已
I'm Saron Yitbarek. Thanks for listening, and keep on coding.